Guide to the Records of the Office of the Associate Provost (Barnett Hamberger) RG.5.2.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Associate Provost (Barnett Hamberger)
1970-1997
1980-1997
New York University Archives
Hamberger, Barnett
RG.5.2.1
8.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 3 flat boxes, and 3 custom preservation boxes
5 videocassettes (vhs)
Barnett (Russ) Hamberger held many positions at New York University, most recently Associate Provost for Academic Program Review from the late 1970s to his retirement in 2016. This collection contains material accumulated and generated by Hamberger in this position, including athletics memorabilia, such as NYU logo lapel pins, keychain, t-shirts, wristwatches, a suit blazer containing the athletics program logo, and a video recording of a women's basketball playoff game. Reports on the management of the Coles Sports and Recreation Center; newspaper clippings; a booklet on the history of NYU student Olympians; and meeting notes from the University Athletic Association (NYU was a founding member) are also included in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the office of Barnett W. (Russ) Hamberger, 2017. The accession number associated with this collection is 2017.042.
Arrangement
Files are arranged in chronological order, followed by t-shirts, hat, and a video cassette stored in the back of the record carton. Memorabilia was rehoused by preservation and four VHS tapes were housed in a shared box.
Biographical Note
Barnett W. (Russ) Hamberger (1940- ) held various positions at New York University since 1965, including Director of Branch Campus Affairs, Assistant to the Vice President for Academic Planning, and Assistant Vice Chancellor for Student Affairs. He received his bachelor's degree from Colgate University and M.A. from New York University. In the 1970s, after serving in various positions within the department of Academic Program Review, he became Associate Provost. While in this position, Hamberger reviewed new programs, served as liaison to the New York State Education Department on academic matters and to the University's regional accrediting agency. He also administered NYU's compliance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) and managed staff who monitored academics and eligibility for NYU's athletics program. Hamberger also served as NYU's voting delegate to the University Athletic Association from its inception in 1985. He retired from his position in 2016.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact university-archives@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact university-archives@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains material accumulated and generated by Associate Provost Barnett Hamberger, including reports and concept papers on the management of the NYU athletics program at the Coles Sports and Recreation Center and meeting materials from the 1980s on NYU's member participation in the University Athletic Association. This collection also contains 1994 and 1997 NCAA women's championship basketball material, including a souvenir program, t-shirts, and video recordings of games and athletics related events. Other memorabilia includes NYU logo lapel pins, a keychain, t-shirts, and a man's suit blazer with an NYU Athletics patch. Logo wrist watches for NYU, Violet Booster Club, and NYU Athletics can also be found in this collection. NYU-published material with contributions by Hamberger include a circa 1988 booklet on NYU student Olympians and a 1970 booklet on students and the governance of NYU.
Minutes (administrative records); T-shirts; Wrist watches; Administrative reports.; Basketball.; Blazers; Lapel pins; College sports -- United States; New York University -- Sports
- Booklet: Students and the Governance of New York University, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Jerome S. Coles Sports and Recreation Center: Management Concept, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Coles Management Review Group Meeting Material, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Clippings, 1981, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- University Athletic Association Meeting Notebook, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Background Paper on Athletic Conference, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- University Athletic Association Briefing Book and Background, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Carrying the Torch: New York University & and The Olympics", circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Report of the NYU Intercollegiate Athletics Advisory Committee, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- NYU Logo Enamel Lapel Pins (3) and Keychain, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- NYU Logo Athletics and Violets Booster Club Wristwatches (7), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- NCAA Women's Basketball Championship Program/Schedule, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- NYU-TV Sports Women's Basketball NCAA Division Championships 1997 Game (NYU vs University of Wisconsin-Eau Claire) Video Recording (Box 1)
- T-shirts (7 total): NYU Pipes and Drums; NYU Women's Basketball Team Championships; NYU Logo with American Flag Motif; "NYU Fans in the Stands"; and University Athletics Association Logo, 1994, 1997, undated (Box 1)
- NYU Logo Athletics Baseball Cap, Undated (Box 1)
- Man's Suit Blazer with NYU Athletics Patch and Suit Buttons, undated (Box 2)
- Founding Committee Gift: Torch Club Logo bookmark from Tiffany & Co., Undated (Box 2)
- Wooden basketball court with hoop commemorating the 1995 Chase/NYU Tournament (Box 3)
- NYU buttons, pins, patches; NYU Athletics coffee mug; Purple corduroy baseball NYU logo with torch hat, undated (Box 4)
- Man's Suit Blazer with NYU Athletics Patch and Suit Buttons, undated (Box 5)
- VHS Students and Jobs at New York University (Box Shared University Archives 023)
- VHS Athletic Fields announcement (Box Shared University Archives 023)
- VHS The Miracle on Washington Square: The New York University Story, undated (Box Shared University Archives 023)
- VHS NYU Sports Complex; Cascilla Spencer, 1992 (Box Shared University Archives 023)